Good morning. Okay, good. That's all working.
This is being turned into a skill right.
So okay. Very important.
Use the GitHub API to start eval states
repositories finish use skill.
Good morning.
My name is Shaun Smith.
As Alan kindly introduced I work at Hugging face on open source
connectivity and MCP and agents initiatives.
Also look after one of the maintainers of our skills repository
and a tool we have called upskill.
So I've heard a lot of people talking about kind of looking
at evaluating and testing skills and so on, so that's worth checking out.
I also maintain a pretty good harness,
I think, called fast-agent, which
which lets you kind of connect a lot of things up and automate
all kinds of things.
So hugging face, we I'm assuming most people
in the audience have got a rough idea of what Hugging Face does.
So we're kind of a central hub for machine learning research.
We host a lot of data sets, we hosted a lot of models,
and it gives people the opportunity to publish research.
And you can connect to those,
connect with a lot of those, collect a lot of those models.
So what we're going to talk talk about today then is we'll talk about
how we've adopted MCP at hugging face in our public facing product.
We'll look at some kind of
analytics and details of how clients connect to our MCP server.
And then we'll kind of look at what some of the current issues with the MCP
protocol are and run through some of the specification changes.
And if we get time, there might be some advice live demos as well.
So so there we go.
So our MCP server has been in production
for a bit over a year, and it's kind of like
a multi-purpose hub for agents and assistance to connect to our services.
So you can search for models, you can inspect data sets,
you can conduct research all through the MCP server.
It's configurable.
So we let you choose
which particular bouquet of tools are active at any particular time.
And we do that in quite a novel way where we let you specify
on the URL what you want active.
Well, we have a user interface that lets you do that as well.
Slightly unusually for a lot of MCP servers, we also
have we allow both authenticated and anonymous access.
So it's actually kind of like a very, very good and easy
MCP server to connect with.
And one of the other
kind of really important things about it is the one that's
actually playing at the moment, is it also acts as an inference gateway.
So through the MCP server you can find and connect
to other models and do things right.
So you can generate images, you can generate videos,
lots of multimedia multimodal multimodal kind of stuff.
So and again everything you're kind of looking at
there is all open wait open source software, the entire stack.
So when we
kind of think about MCP, I'll just kind of
quickly kind of introduce what MCP is.
I'm sure most people are already fairly familiar, but
the MCP protocol
by its design was designed to be bidirectional.
Okay.
So the kind of the basic idea was that you would have MCP clients
and they would connect to MCP servers,
and they'd almost been this kind of peer to peer relationship,
where the pairings of them would work together to to kind of modify
the context of the, of what you were using.
Okay.
So MCP clients can obviously use tools and prompts and so on.
And the idea being that MCP servers could also make requests to the client
and use things like the LM attached or the file system attached.
So again, quite similar to the way that LSP
servers work, work with Ides
now kind
of almost famously when it was launched,
MCP launched with two transports local transport, which
which runs in normally the same processes as your application
can access the file system and so on, and also a remote transport called SSE.
But there was no authentication at all.
Shortly afterwards,
it was kind of quite clear that the SAC transport
was pretty difficult to work with in that in that way.
So a new transport
was launched called stream of HTTP to make it a bit easier to deploy.
And at that time, authentication
was also added, with the MCP server
meant to be acting as an authorization server, which again turned out to be
slightly too complicated, and so ultimately a better design to use.
A water resource server was then introduced.
And that's kind of where we where we kicked off.
So at launch time for us about 12 months ago,
we were still at the point where we weren't sure
whether to use the SSE transport
or how to tackle their walls, but we kind of just went right.
We're doing the new stuff
now when
when we kind of first launch the graph that you're seeing here,
the yellow bars are showing the number of initializations that we get per day.
And this is on a week by week basis.
And the blue line is showing how many connections are coming through.
Using an adapter that lets you use a standard IO client with a remote server.
Because this was a lot of the very, very early clients
only really had standard IO support.
So there was a tool that kind of let
you just connect your ordinary client through to your remote server.
And as you can see, the,
you know,
the traffic's kind of dropped off and we can kind of zoom in
and look at particular clients so we can say,
right, well, actually, Claude Code initially only had standard IO support.
And you can see that the traffic kind of drops off.
And at the moment, Claude, code usage looks like it's
probably dropping off because because of the day I took the data.
But again, a very, very few remote connections.
So by and large, you know, the the migration away from local
to remote services pretty much done.
We'll look at a little bit more of that in a moment.
The other kind of question that you'll often,
you'll often want to answer is if I've got lots of MCP clients
and they're all connecting to my server, what's actually going on?
And we often kind of think, right, well,
is lots of initializations a good thing?
Do I measure the number of tool calls?
What kind of things make sense to understand.
So as you can see the blue line there is showing tool
calls against initializations.
That big spike by the way was a performance test
from, from one of the inference providers that that
I discovered.
About.
But yeah.
So feel free to have, you know, use our server that kind of thing.
But polite to talk to me first.
So when it comes to kind
of understanding activity on the MCP server, there's kind of a few things
to think about if you're kind of running it in production.
And the first one is quite often you might think that initializations
might be quite a good, a good thing to to track.
And it's not really the case because while in some clients, initializations
will kind of mean that you've got an ambient installation, because every time
someone opens their tool, it connects to our server.
In other cases, clients will cache and only initialize
when they make it all call.
We also tend to find a lot of clients are not necessarily as stable
as they should be, and will sometimes get into runaway loops where they kind of
just carry on initializing and causing a bit of trouble.
The other one, which we kind of look at is tool calls.
Now, often people will think, well, actually, you know, we're doing better
if we've got more tool calls.
And that's not necessarily the case, because if you get lots of repeated
tool calls, that may simply mean that your tool design
is causing confusion to the downstream agent.
And again, someone using
this through an through an interactive chatter system that's going to be doing
something quite different to what they would be doing
if they were using it interactively through, say, ChatGPT.
So what we tend
to or what I tend to look at is session conversion.
So how many clients connect and then make at least one tool call.
And that's quite, quite an interesting count for me on the right.
Again, the the session conversion efficiency
kind of shows some of the main clients that attached to us,
the ones at the top will connect and make a tool call.
So OpenMCP: 96.2% of the time.
No surprise, it's the agent builder that does that because of the nature
of how it's built.
MCP remote fallback test.
Of course, it's a fallback test. It never makes it all call.
So more efficiency isn't necessarily better because if
you've incorrectly cached it at all list,
you're not going to be making a call to the MCP server itself.
So these are some quite difficult things to balance
when kind of trying to understand activity.
But if we look at the last few weeks,
Codex is a very efficient client
and is more and more people have kind of gone on to Codex.
One thing I've actually seen here
is, is the the conversion rate has kind of gone up.
And again, we can see that there's still an increasing amount
of useful session to talk or conversion
traffic.
We also publish
an data set, which contains
a kind of list of all of the clients that we've seen and their capabilities.
So if you kind of want to have a look at what version
clients are at, what capabilities or extensions they've got installed,
then that data set is a very, very good place to start.
So have a look, check it out because,
you know, probably be publishing a bit more data through there fairly soon.
Now in production,
the MCP kind of gives us a couple of challenges.
And the main challenge is comes back from that initial design, right?
Which is that if I have a kind of a client and servant pairing,
there's an assumption in the protocol that the
the relationship between them is stateful.
So what's actually happening here is, is that the client will make a request
to the server, and the server says I've initialized.
And then the client sends back a notification and they've kind of hand
shaken.
So we've already kind of two messages from the client
to the server in before we've actually established a session.
After that, the client then will normally check and say, right,
well give me the list of tools,
give me the list of prompts, give me the list of resources.
We're so we're now kind of we're at four calls in before we've actually even
we've actually even serviced anything.
And then finally we'll get a tool call
in the information.
We'll go back to the client.
Now again kind of typically
what what we'll see in these kind of scenarios is if we've got state
at both the client and the server, that starts to get rather
rather tricky to manage.
And it's also very, very chatty.
So I kind of ran this I think it was on Sunday morning.
This number kind of varies a bit based on the mix of clients we've recently seen.
But at the moment, for every 10 million protocol messages that we get.
So these are the kind of MCP protocol methods and calls, 1.2
million of them are initialize events, which can may be interesting,
but actually only 62,000 of them at all calls.
So the kind of overhead of managing that stateful connection
is, is quite high from from a protocol level.
Now there is a kind of semi documented
undocumented mode where you can kind of run MCP stateless.
It's a bit ambiguous, but if you do that,
you lose any ability to kind of capture analytics.
So some of the challenges then we have with with stateful.
So one is that ambiguity around, around the protocol,
the use of elicitation and sampling, if you've got server
initiated requests, mean that you need to maintain an open channel.
Okay.
So one of the things that we were quite keen on trying when we first
launched was to send what are called tool list change notifications.
So the MCP server, if it wants to offer different tools, will notify the client.
And the client can then offer them.
But actually in practice, that's a very, very difficult thing to do,
especially on a public server.
As I mentioned, session state and understanding
that is not quite precisely defined enough in the protocol.
So a standard IO server, you kind of just connect,
you've got a process and you talk to it a remote server,
you have an MCP session ID, it doesn't necessarily match up
an operationally having sticky sessions and load balancers,
which need to inspect the traffic
to send it to the right server, means that doing server upgrades, resilience,
or kind of standard scaling practice becomes very, very difficult.
The other challenge as well is SSE connection
and cut off times make a lot of that quite, quite difficult as well.
So those are some of the
challenges and kind of what we see in production. So.
It's been probably about over the last ten months
then been working with the MCP transports working group.
We've got people from Google and Microsoft and everybody
contributing to that kind of sharing the production data,
sharing our experience of how to actually deploy this.
And we now in the new release candidate specification, have some fairly
big changes to the protocol to actually make this easier and simpler to deploy.
And I think, you know, to get get a lot more, a lot more value out of.
So kind of the first thing to kind of think about then is this, that
this is actually the first time that we've had this type of change
to the protocol, where we now have the standard IO protocol changing
the JSON-RPC messages that you send backwards and forwards
across it are going to be different.
And then we also, of course, have a new a new way of connecting
to remote servers with with the stateless HTTP transport.
So let's kind of start to dive into some of those changes.
So actually the first the first
kind of most important one of those is just simply simplifying it.
So the first the first one there is taking away the ability
for service to communicate with clients without the client
having sent you a message first.
And the team at anthropic actually did some analysis
on all of the open source servers, all the open source servers that they
can find, and all of the other MCP servers they could find.
And it turns out that across 100 million tokens of searching,
the only person to use this feature is is on stage right now.
So I'm now going to
try a very ill advised demonstration because
let's see if we can
let's see if we can do this. So.
Yeah so so MCP webcam then
is is a very very useful, very, very useful application
which lets you do things like if I say look through the webcam, everyone's smile.
Let's see if this will actually work.
This is a good kind of test of network.
And there we go.
Yeah. Perfect. So yeah.
So so webcam then it's a fairly straightforward MCP server
which lets you kind of use a user webcam through MCP.
So obviously a very, very useful thing.
Now the feature the the feature
that we're going to be losing from MCP webcam as a result of this change.
And this is, as I say, the kind of one example of the world in the world is.
Let me just refresh that.
Actually, I think I need to
I will just quickly reconnect that because now I haven't gone to the.
Having gone to the risk
of trying to do a live demonstration, I may as well see it through. There we go.
Okay, so if I hit sample, what's actually happening now is the webcam.
MCP server is connecting to the client,
and now the client is giving a description of of border.
Sure. Yeah.
It's giving a description of what it's seen.
This is a good example of why context engineering matters
because you don't particularly don't necessarily want the
AI view of you.
So we're simplifying it.
We're taking away the ability
for clients, the ability for service to talk to clients without having
first had a message in from the, from the client.
And that means we can simplify
the network, the network aspects quite a lot as well.
So sampling routes going and logging as well.
If you're if you're a real protocol peeper
huge then
is we're taking away that initialization handshake.
Right.
So we're typically the MCP server standard IO or remote would send a
initialized request and go through that whole kind of handshaking
and save the capabilities on either side.
That's just going okay.
So if you still need to find out the server capabilities
before you're actually interacting with it, there's a discover endpoint
that you can call that will give you a probe to
to get that, particularly if you want to show it in your user
experience if prompts and resources are available.
So that's great.
And if you are using those list change notifications or resource subscriptions,
there is still an endpoint that you that your client can call
to get those notifications. Okay.
But again, it's a big a big improvement, a big simplification.
Another one
of my own actually this is one of my favorites is cache control.
So when an MCP server
gives you the list of tools,
we can now say that list of tools is probably not
going to change for the next hour or the next couple of days,
which means that clients can then cache it.
Even more importantly, it's where you have a fleet of clients.
The server can indicate that it's safe to share that tallest amongst
a whole load of clients,
which means that you'll be able to discover MCP server information
cache so you don't have to discover it on each connection.
And you can also then discover that
from other offline stores like the MCP server card.
So a kind of a manifest that tells you all about
that MCP server.
And again, that doesn't necessarily overwrite.
If you get to all this change notification,
all of those things still take precedence.
But that kind of caching behavior gives us huge scope to kind of,
you know, just improve the overall user experience for
for both agents and users and operations teams.
One of the
you'll have noticed on that client side, there were three features.
Their roots, sampling, elicitation, elicitation
are the ability for the NCP server when you make a request to it
to kind of pause and say, right, I need some user guidance,
you've sent me a message to drop the database.
I'm going to pop up a message or a window.
Is it okay to drop that database?
And the user can then say yes, no or or so on.
So you can you can supply extra information through
through the deterministic channel.
Now the challenge with the current elicitation design is again, it kind of assumes that
the server and the client managing state between them.
So it just kind of sends small messages.
So what we're actually going to do instead
is the client will send a request to the server.
The server will respond rather than having a direct result.
It will say, actually I need to stop and get some input.
The MCP client can then handle the user, the user facing input,
and then it can send both that original request and the response
to the request back to the server for processing the next turn.
So very, very similar to the way that a
API works works today.
And again, this is I think this is going to be
an absolutely huge feature with HTTP standardization.
And I think I'll, I'll tell you what it is first,
then we'll talk about why I think it's exciting.
So for standardization, what we're doing is first of all,
we're making sure that certain MCP information.
So if we think about MCP it uses JSON-RPC.
So you have these kind of JSON RPC packets that the server reads
and then process and then sensitive JSON RPC response.
And of course if you've got any kind of network infrastructure
that means it needs to inspect the JSON packet, unpack it,
which is a fairly expensive operation.
So firstly, we're guaranteeing that certain information in the request
is in the HTTP headers, which is going to make it very, very simple to route.
Super powerful is the in tool descriptions, you'll be able to say
I want this particular parameter copied into the headers okay.
So that means for example.
So I'll just put a spec on the on the screen.
So that means for example, if I've got an image generation space
I can actually find, find that out at network
routing time and divert it to the appropriate server to to handle it.
Okay.
So it opens up completely new deployment options for how you may want to.
I want to
supply this kind of stuff to agents.
So again that means as I say it's visible to network infrastructure.
It means that you can then route tools wherever you go.
So for for MCP gateway companies, MCP proxy companies, these
kind of features are going to be very, very important for for efficiency.
So once we've done all of those changes and we have the Usdc out,
that means that,
you know,
rather than that kind of failure, long and laborious handshake to get things done.
And you're kind of potentially looking at all of the excited
J star PC packets and so on, instead will be able to have much,
much higher performance in the protocol level itself.
But also if you kind of think about the utility of this for
from an agent's perspective, the ability that you can connect
to an authorized set of tools with a single URL is extremely important.
And the fact that things like the tallest description
and other metadata about the server will be available out of band mean
that all of a sudden, connecting to authorized endpoints to do
arbitrary agent workloads, dispatching jobs, doing other,
doing other inference becomes becomes far more compelling.
Okay, so these changes open up a whole
load of new use cases that just didn't exist before.
And because it's MCP, that single URL
to get to an authenticated ready resource is super important.
So where are we?
Migration path is face straightforward.
The release candidate specification is released I think it was last week.
So you can see all of the work we've been doing over over the last few months.
Some of the debates and discussions that have been had.
Aim is to have beta SDKs by the end of this month,
and then the planned protocol release date is the 28th of July.
Just one final thing before I stop.
I'm just going to go slightly over time now is we've
kind of quite keen on building the right agent infrastructure.
So we have a tool called Monte, which is a sandbox
for running agent generated Python code.
And we're co-sponsoring the bounty.
So so have a, have a look at that.
If you're particularly good at breaking rust sandboxes.
We definitely like to like to help get that infrastructure layer more secure.
So with that I think that's my time up.
Thank you very much.
Yeah.
We do actually have a few minutes for questions.
If there are any questions,
put your hand up and we'll get a microphone to you somehow.
First ones here if you.
Hello.
Thank you for your presentation.
In your opinion, what separates companies
that are generally building a genetic infrastructure from
those that are just wrapping LLM APIs with workflows?
So I didn't catch the first part of the question. Sorry.
The first one is, in your opinion, what separates companies that are
generally building a infrastructure from those that are just wrapping
LLM APIs with workflows?
Testing mostly
would be we'd be with you there.
I mean, I don't have.
The industry's, I think
very, very quick at deciding that one thing is very good or very, very bad.
I think that unless you've kind of got a good idea
as to what it is you're trying to do with inference
and how you're designing the context window, sometimes
actually directly wrapping an API is absolutely the right thing to do.
And other times, of course, it's absolutely not.
So I think the difference
is whether or not you've actually tested and evaluate those differences.
And slightly conceptual question.
When you are trying to decide whether it's best
to use a silly tool for that MCP server for that.
How would you tell the difference to make sure
the agent is working and performing better?
So so the question is.
So the the question is
if we can choose between CLI and an MCP, let's say playwright.
Oh yeah. Yeah. Right. MCP.
Oh. So I think probably with some of these changes
those things start to converge slightly as well.
MCP is very very good if you want to access
remote resources where.
So for example if I'm going to if I want to run a remote training job,
then dispatching a job through MCP is actually quite a nice, secure
way of doing it, rather than, say, bringing all of the data down.
But we,
you know, we provide access to our services through both
our hugging face CLI and provide them through both the
through the MCP server.
And I would say, I think
for when we kind of look at the client usage, it varies a lot.
MCC tend to be
preferred in enterprises because you can have much tighter
control over what's deployed on what machine and where.
So certainly a lot of the kind of coding tool traffic we see, I suspect,
is probably from those kind of scenarios where MCP really works very, very well.
And we kind of see this with the MCP apps extension is interactive applications.
So things like ChatGPT, because again, it's very,
very easy to connect those things up
and then you can have very rich interactive experiences.
So it's been kind of in my mind for quite a long time.
You know, to a certain extent we've kind of got those two audiences
and, you know,
we may want to start adapting how we how we deploy some of those tools as a result.
But yeah, it's a good, very good question.
Any more for any more final question.
Okay.
Final round. Applause. Thank you so much Sean Smith.